<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise or sermon of Henry Bullynger: much fruitfull and necessarye for this tyme, concernynge magistrates and obedience of subiectes Also concernyng the affayres of warre, and what scryptures make mension thereof. whether christen powers may war against their ennemies. And whither it be laufull for a christyan to beare the office of a magistrate, and of the duety of souldiers with many other holsom instructions for captaynes [and] souldiers both. Made in the yeare of our lorde. M. D. xlix.</title>
            <title>Sermonum decades qinque. English. Selections</title>
            <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1549</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 57 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 35 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17223</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4079</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S110959</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99846403</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99846403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">11367</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17223)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 11367)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 28:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise or sermon of Henry Bullynger: much fruitfull and necessarye for this tyme, concernynge magistrates and obedience of subiectes Also concernyng the affayres of warre, and what scryptures make mension thereof. whether christen powers may war against their ennemies. And whither it be laufull for a christyan to beare the office of a magistrate, and of the duety of souldiers with many other holsom instructions for captaynes [and] souldiers both. Made in the yeare of our lorde. M. D. xlix.</title>
                  <title>Sermonum decades qinque. English. Selections</title>
                  <author>Bullinger, Heinrich, 1504-1575.</author>
                  <author>Lynne, Walter.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Impri[n]ted [by W. Powell?] for Gwalter Lynne dwellynge vpon Somers Kaye by Byllynges gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>In the yeare of our lord god. M. D. xlix, The xxiii day of August] [1549]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translated from decade 2, sermon 9 of: Sermonum decades quinque.</note>
                  <note>Translated by: Walter Lynne.</note>
                  <note>Is a different translation from that in STC 4056--STC.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name suggested by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures A-D E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:1"/>
            <p>A treatiſe or Sermon of Henry Bullynger, much fruitfull and neceſſarye for this tyme, concernynge magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and obedience of ſubiectes. Alſo concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng the affayres of warre, and what ſcryptures make menſion thereof. whether chriſten powers may war againſt their ennemies. And whither it be laufull for a chriſtyan to beare the office of a magiſtrate, and of the duety of ſouldiers with many other holſom inſtructions for captaynes &amp; ſouldiers both. Made in the yere of our lorde. M.D. xlix I.F.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Let euerye ſubiect ſubmyt hym ſelfe vnto the aucthoritie of the hygher powers. For ther is no po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wer but of god. The powers that be, are ordeyned of god. <bibl>Ro. xii. a Sapi. vi. a i. Pet. ii. b.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>My ſonne feare thou the Lorde and the Kynge, and kepe no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſlaunderers for their deſtruccion ſhal come ſodenly. <bibl>prouerb .xxiiii. And, prouerb, xx.</bibl>
            </p>
            <p>The Kynge oughte to be feared as the roaring of a Lyon, whoſo prouoketh hym vnto anger, offen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth agaynſt his owne ſoule. <bibl>pro. xx. a .xxiiii. c.</bibl>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:2"/>
            <head>¶ To the moſt excellent Prince Edward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .vi. by the grace of God Kyng of England, Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and Itlande, defendoure of the fayth, and in earthe of the churche of englande and Irelande imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly vnder God ſuppreme head, your graces humble ſubiect and dayly orator Gwalter Lyn wyſſheth aboundaunce of al grace, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, with a long and proſperous raygne.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſideringe (moſt mygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Prynce), what greate benifites I haue receyued of this your
<pb facs="tcp:11367:3"/> maieſties realme of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande which hath ſo mani yeares nouriſhed and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coured my poore lyfe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto. I thought my ſelf no leſſe bound of very du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty but to ſhew ſome office of recompenſation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. Againe conſideringe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feruent proceadynge of your maieſtie in ſettynge forth the worde of god, &amp; alſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towardnes of moſte your ſubiectes which as a rype harueſt do lacke but workemen, to ſet them for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>warde, I thoughte I coulde gratyfy in no other
<pb facs="tcp:11367:3"/> thynge more both youre moſte graciouſe entente &amp; the deſyre of this youre realm, which now I take for myne owne natiue cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tre, than to ſerch out ſome neceſſary doctryne, whiche coulde do all my countrye men good. Vpon the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che conſideracion here I brought out of latine into englyſh a worke of Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenger moſt fruytfull &amp; expedient for all tymes na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely for this tyme moſte neceſſary, concernynge the ordre of a common wealth the inſtitution of magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates,
<pb facs="tcp:11367:4"/> the vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſworde the obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſubiectes, the miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of warres, the inſtruction of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours. Whyche thinges I think to be ſo neceſſary for theſe daies, that nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g can come in more meite time or place. And as this worke of this excellent au<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſemyth to me moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellently handeled full of moſt notable hiſtores, and excellent doctrine, ſo I coulde fynde no other ſo meite to dedicate it vnto, as to your excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t maieſty to whom not only I dedi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate
<pb facs="tcp:11367:4"/> this worke and labor of myne, but body life and goodes to your gracious pleaſure, wyth my conty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nuall prayer alſo to al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myghty God longe to pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſpere your floriſhing ſtate to his glori and forthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his welbeloued church. Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true and obedient ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iect Gwalter Lynne.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:5"/>
            <head>Henry Boullynger concerning Magiſtrates and Subiectes</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Arre is a thing perteyninge to the ſworde whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che is gyuen of god to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrats.<note place="margin">Sapi. vt. a prou. cx. &amp; ano. xxiiiic rom. xiii. a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>irum. iii. a 1. Pet: ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> For ſo I declared in my laſt ſermon, that this ſword in the magiſtrates handes hath two vſes: other to punyſh treſpaſers, or elles to repelle and diſtroy our open ennemies with al ſuch other like rebellious &amp; ſedicious cyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſins, &amp; ſubiectes. what ſoeuer they be. But here commith a dout in many mens heades whether it be lawfull for mageſtrates to kepe warre.<note place="margin">Whyther it be lawfull for mage<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates to wares</note> And I marueyll that men can be ſo blynd in a thing ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent. For yf it be lawful for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates by gods lawe to puniſh
<pb facs="tcp:11367:5"/> treſpaſſers, theues, &amp; murderers who ſo euer noyeth the common wealth, whether they be fewe or many, that is no matter, as I de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared to you yeſter daye, by the ſame lawe lykewiſe is it lawfull for them to inuade and purſue with armes rebelles and ſeditious cyteſyns, or anye forayne enemye who ſo euer entende the ſame by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> colour of warre, that theues and murderers do practiſe within the realme.</p>
            <p>Truth it is that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> diuine prophet ſayth prophecieng of vs Chriſten men.<note place="margin">Eſay. ii a Ioel. iii. b</note> They ſhal turne their ſwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to mattoks, and their ſperes to ſyethes. For Chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kepe peace with al men, and vtterly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde al fyghthing,<note place="margin">eeclr. xxxl, b Iob lii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Mate vii: a Luc, vi, c</note> for ſo do they to other as they would be done to them ſelues. But for bycauſe all
<pb facs="tcp:11367:6"/> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not of one nature, but mani perturbers, wicked murtherers, &amp; oppreſſors be myxt amongeſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; quiet citeſins, as cruel wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt ſimpleſhepe, therfore doth god permit from heauen the ſword to the magiſtrates for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fence of the innocentes:<note place="margin">Rom xiii a</note> Neither is it euer red in anye place but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we lawfully may oppreſſe &amp; deſtroye wolues, bores, beares, &amp; all ſuche beaſtes which be noyſom to me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or cattel. And why then is it not as lawful w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> war &amp; viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de the wicked force of viole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derers, ſetng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al ſuch murderers, robbers, barbarous enmies, ſediti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous citeſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s do littel or nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from wilde beaſtes. Certes, the ſcripture callith the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with no other name, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> beaſtes, to this alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſence of natur. Here to alſo the doctrin of religion and
<pb facs="tcp:11367:6"/> faith agreith. Yf it be poſſible ſaith thapoſtle, ſo much as in you lyeth, haue peace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al men,<note place="margin">rom. xii. c Heb. xii, c</note> reuen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynge not your ſelues. Note, ſo much as is in you he ſayth. And if it be poſſible. For or els it folowet after, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate beareth not a ſworde for nought.<note place="margin">rom. xlii a</note> As who ſhuld ſay for ſuch maner of perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as do maligne &amp; diſquiet honeſt &amp; quiet me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wold faine liue in reſt &amp; cannot. Hereto alſo agre y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the moſt holieſt men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euer wer, which did war for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of their country, &amp; of innocentes, As I de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clared to you out of ſ. Pa. to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre. whan I ſhewed you in the .v. commandement, what duty euery man oweth to his country. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to wil I annexe certayne places out of ſ. Auſtin.<note place="margin">Euſilib. xx, Capl xxv</note> diſputed agaynſt Fauſtus Manicheus .li.xx c. lxxv
<pb facs="tcp:11367:7"/> Neyther yet ſayth he, let a man ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>horre or meruell at the battayles donne by Moſes,<note place="margin">pro: xvil. Num. xx: and: xxi. dede xx. &amp;c:</note> for in them alſo he folowed gods commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dement, not for any eigernes, but for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience ſake. For whan he was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced therto by god, he exceded not in rigour, but only recompen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thynges worthy to mens de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing and brought feare vpon ſuch as were well worthy. For what thyng can a man reproue in warres becauſe men do dye whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che muſt dye once,<note place="margin">hebre. ix d</note> wherbye peace may follow? To put blame in this, is not a ſygne of religiouſe men but of timerous, perſons.</p>
            <p>The pleaſure in hurting, outragi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous in reuenging, an vnplacable ſtomack, wylde rebellynge gredi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to gett dominion, and ſuche lyke, theſe be they whiche be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely
<pb facs="tcp:11367:7"/> reproued in warre, and not only reproued, but alſo puniſhed. Againſt the vyolence of oure ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaryes, good men may right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully warre, other by gods lawe, or by any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of ſuperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or powers, beyng in ſuch vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where their powers other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth any ſuch thyng, or byn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth them to obedience, Or elles Saynt Ihon Baptiſte,<note place="margin">Luce ciii. d</note> whan the ſouldiers came to hym to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, aſkynge what they ſhuld do: he myght haue anſwered them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne. Caſt away your harnes, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nounce your warrfarre, ſtrike no man, wounde no man, ouerthrow no body: but bycauſe he dydde ſee theym in doynge theſe thynges in warrfayre to be no murtherers but myniſters of the law, neyther reuengeres of their own iniuries,
<pb facs="tcp:11367:8"/> but defenders of publyke wealth, he ſayde to them, ſtryke no body, wrangle w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> no man, be content w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your own ſtipende. But bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Manichees be wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to deſpiſe and blaſpheme Ihon, lette them heare our lord Ieſu chriſt hym ſelf, com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunding the ſame ſtipend to be gyuen to ceſar, which Ihon aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſited the ſouldiours to be content with al: Gyue vnto Ceaſar ſayth chriſt,<note place="margin">Matt xx it c and xvi: d roma. x.ii b</note> the thinges which are Cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, &amp; vnto god, thoſe thinges y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are gods. For therfore be tributs payd, wherby warres maye be wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged, &amp; ſouldiours mainteined for neceſſite of war. So he doth wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely alſo commend the faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> centurion ſaying. And I am a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſet here vnder powers,<note place="margin">Mat viii a Luc vi: a</note> hauing vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der me ſouldiours, and I ſaye to hym goe, and he goeth, and to an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other
<pb facs="tcp:11367:8"/> come &amp; he comith. And to my ſeruaunt do this &amp; he doth it, we ſe he commendeth his faythe therfore, but he byddeth him not to forſake the wars. Hytherto alſo perteineth the chapt. folowynge .lxxv. &amp; .lxxvi. &amp;c. But here I am content to ſpare you, &amp; not to ouer burden you w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to prolyx recitinge of ſentences. Thus much haue I ſpoken hetherto for that, that it is lawful for magiſtrates to warre. And vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this we gather that ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes<note place="margin">Subiectes mir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t obeys theyr pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers comman<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng warre</note> lykewiſe may lawfully &amp; w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out reprehenſion go &amp; feighte in warfare, when they be commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the magiſtrates ſo to do.</p>
            <p>But yf it be ſo that the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes cauſles do ſet vpon to ſlay the innocentes and vngylty perſons, I haue declared in my formar ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mons,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et. iiii and .v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> in this caſe the magiſtrats co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are not to be obeied
<pb facs="tcp:11367:9"/> Therfore let the magiſtrates take hyde leſſe they abuſe their aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite.<note place="margin">Warre is a peregous thyng</note> And all though it be lawfull for the Magiſtrates to kepe warr for iuſt and neceſſary cauſes, yet is warre a moſt daungerous thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and bringeth with it hepes of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite troubles. And thus be ſuch men punyſhed dyuerſe tymes, whome no gentyl admonition ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> moue all be it many innocent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons with ſuch be puniſhed amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Nowe many tymes it happeneth that ſouldiours forget them ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and breake al good ordre pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uokyng the myghti angre of god vpon their heades, what kynde of myſcheyfe is in al the worlde but it is vſed in warre or what kynde of miſery is there that is not here Fyrſt by warre ſpryngeth dearth and vtter ſcaſety of al thynges,
<pb facs="tcp:11367:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> For the wayes be ſtopped, the torne troden downe, townes ſet on fyre, vitalle diſtroied &amp; waſted, all occupations and marchandiſe ceaſe, both riche and poore decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: In warre the mooſt valiante ſoneſt deſtroyed, the towards thei retyre &amp; ſaue them ſelues whyles greater afterclappes do fal vpon them. The moſt vyle ruffynes, moſt auaunced, which abuſe men more lyke beaſtes then other.</p>
            <p>All is full of murning on euerye ſyde: Wydowes bewayle: father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les children lament and be deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, Greate riches prouyded for nede to come, cleane ſpoyled, hole cites ſet a fyre,<note place="margin">Eſay. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and v</note> vyrgynes an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mared mayde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s defyled: Al ſhame al honeſty ſet a ſyde: no reuerence to age: All maner of ryght all la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes vnregarded: al holy religion
<pb facs="tcp:11367:10"/> and ſtudies cleane vnder foote, vyle vacaboundes and deſperate dreuylles rule all the toſte. And therfore in ſcripture warre is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the ſcourge of god.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Warre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eth ſcourge of god</p>
                  <p>Leuit xxvi ii Reg. xxiiii Deut xxviii</p>
               </note> This ſcourge doth god lyghtly inferre vpon incurrable and obſtinat deſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſers of his word. For this cauſe was the citie of Hieruſalem ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted with all the whole nations of the Iewes,<note place="margin">Mat. xxiii. e Luce xiii d</note> for as the lord ſaith they dyd not know y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> day of their viſitation, but rather thei did ſhed the bloud of the lordes apoſtles, ſo brynging vpon their own heades al the bloud,<note place="margin">Gene iiii b ii. par xxiiii d</note> ſhedde from fyrſte Abell the iuſte, vnto zacharye.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Num xxi and xxxiii &amp;c</note>The Chananites for murder, idolatrye, inceſt, and for abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable letchery were vtterly deua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted. The Moabites, as Eſaie ſaith,<note place="margin">Eſay. xv and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vi.</note> periſhed for theirr cueltein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clemenci, and proud diſpiſinge of
<pb facs="tcp:11367:10"/> the pore. The Niniuites did infeſt other nations with vniuſt warres wherefore thei were ſerued with lyke meaſure. Agayne of other countreis, as we reede in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Nahum,<note place="margin">Nahum ii and iii</note> Micheas in the vi cap. declareth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth warre to the vniuſt,<note place="margin">The cauſes of warre</note> for their auarice, &amp; fraude vſynge. In Ieremye<note place="margin">Ierem v <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c</note> arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy and pryde, in Eſaye<note place="margin">Eſay v <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ryote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes exceſſe and dronckennes, are noted to be the cauſes of warre. Farthermore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incommodities of war do cleaue ſo hard to realmes &amp; publik weales, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei cannot af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward be remoued or ſhaken of whan we wold, nether by humane policie, nor leages, nor riches, nor defence, ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, nor power, as we may ſe in Abdias.<note place="margin">Abdias <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyncere and harty conuerſion to god reme<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyeth thys, as Ieremy in .v.<note place="margin">Ierem v <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> capt. do teſtifie. This true conuerſion
<pb facs="tcp:11367:11"/> to god ſtandeth fyrſt in the confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſion and knowledge of our owne wyckednes, than in a ſewer fayth to haue remiſſion of oure ſynnes by grace and merite of oure lorde Ieſus chriſt.<note place="margin">Roma. v and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i.</note> Thyrdly in a perfect hatred, and renounſynge of cure formare iniquite in ſtudye of iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce, innocency, charite, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vertues: fynally in continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all prayer &amp; oration.</p>
            <p>Againe to ſome a man ſhall ſee war<note place="margin">Warre pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fitable to ſome</note> bryngeth much profyt vtilite and vnnumerable ryches, with no damage or lytel at all. Such was the battayle of the Iſraelytes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Chananaeis, Ioſue<note place="margin">Ioſua, iii c and xvi, b</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge theyr captayne.</p>
            <p>I wolde not heare the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of warre ſhuld allure any fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuſtice and equite. For ſo many tymes it happenyth that whyle
<pb facs="tcp:11367:11"/> Magiſtrates thinke to haue a iuſt occaſion to warre agaynſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to puniſh offenders,<note place="margin">The good ſome tymes be ouercome of the wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</note> god of his pryue iuſtice reaturneth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame occaſion vpon them ſelues in prouokyng them, wherby ther ſynnes may be punyſhed of them whome they intende to perſecute. Examples we haue manyfeſte in ſcriptures.<note place="margin">Iud ſeu xix and .xx</note>
            </p>
            <p>The eleuen tribes of Iſrael pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed mooſt iuſt warre againſt the Beniamites, thynkynge to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenge a wycked facte commytted by certaine leud loſels, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che loſelles, the whole tribe tooke parte, communicatinge with their vngraciouſnes, yet were they put to the worſt and foyled of the wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked ſort.<note place="margin">i reg ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and v</note> The Iſraelites wente about to expell the violence of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> idolatrouſe phyliſtianes vnder
<pb facs="tcp:11367:12"/> Hely their preiſte yet were they o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrowne in battayle, &amp; the arke of god caried away into the cities of idolatours.<note place="margin">iiii reg. xxiii, ii. pa. xxxv d</note> So y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good kynge Ioſias was ſlain of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chaldeis by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe the entent of god was to ſco<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>urge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuch euils which he wold not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good king to behold nothing ſo deſeruing. Wherupon this note is to be learned, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of religion<note place="margin">Religion is not ſene by victory.</note> goyth not by the victorye of any natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or by ouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>throw, as though y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion were y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better, whoſe part had the vpper hande, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the worſte religion, whoſe part had y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſt. For reli<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gion alwaies muſt be ſequeſtrede from the perſon &amp; reſpecte of men which for diuerſe cauſes be diuerſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly viſited of the lorde.</p>
            <p>All theſe thinges admoniſh vs, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Magiſtrates had nede of much
<pb facs="tcp:11367:12"/> and great feare of god, in takyng vp or in laying downe their war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, leſt perchaunſe in flyenge the ſmoke thei fall into the fyre, or whyle they ſtudye to eſchue one harme, by eſchuyng therof, do pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheſſe to them ſelues many moo &amp; greater. Wherfore it is requiſite that prynces fyrſt before al thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges do thorowly conſidre the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of their warres.<note place="margin">The cauſes of warre muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidered</note> Now there be mani cauſes and ſundry, but theſe lightly the greateſte. For other y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> magiſtrate is enforced ſeinge hys holdes and munimentes in hys realme to be inuaded with ſeige, then he muſt nedes healpe and re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulſe hys ennemie. For it were to much vnfaithfulnes to forſake ſo diſloyally hys cyteis &amp; fortres in ſuch extreme peryll. Or elles the magiſtrate by reaſon of hys of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce is conſtrayned to attempte
<pb facs="tcp:11367:13"/> warre againſt incurable perſons whome the ſentence of the lorde doth condemne, &amp; byddeth to beat downe vtterly without al pyte.</p>
            <p>So as Moſes dyd warre agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt the Madianites Saule againſte Amalechetes Of this maner be al ſuche kyndes of warre wherwith men be oppreſſed,<note place="margin">Num xxv and xxxi i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> xv</note> whiche by the vncureable malyce of theirs, wyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nedes peryſh and make other pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryſh with them alſo, which reiect all iuſtice, and equite, al ſette on myſcheif &amp; ſo ſtubbornly continu.<note place="margin">Iudic xx and xxi Marke wel rebellions</note> Such were the Beniamites wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were diſtroyed wyth ſworde and fyer: ſuche be nowe a dayes theſe obſtinate and ſedicious tray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours troblelers of publick ſocie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty as was ons Abſolon and Seba the ſonne of Bochrus whyche be mentioned in the ſeconde boke of<note place="margin">Samu ii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Reg. xiii xiiii xv xvi xvii xviii</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11367:13"/> Samuel.<note place="margin">Warre for religion.</note> Herto atpartayne alſo ſuch warres acheued againſt Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laters, and oppreſſors of catholik fayth. for trew relygio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſake. Thei be in a wrong dreame which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke no war ought to be attempted for relygion.</p>
            <p>The lorde reſtrayned Peter ſtry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge with the ſworde:<note place="margin">Mat xxvi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Luce xxii d Ioh xviii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Truth I graunt he reſtrained hym as an Apoſtle, he forbadde not the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate the ouerſight of religion, but that he myght defend the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of our faith. Yf the magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes maye lawfullye defende viler thinges, as libertye, goodes, bode<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly honeſtye, and lyfe. &amp;c. Howe much more may he defende grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thinges, yea which be the grea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſt thinges of all? For what can be greater than true religion:<note place="margin">Deut xiii and xvii b</note> V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this we haue an expreſſe com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundement
<pb facs="tcp:11367:14"/> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord in Deutro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">Marke wel</note> For the lorde commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cite vnder what magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trate ſo euer he be, which defyleth from god &amp; his worſhyp, to be let vpon with warre and vtterly to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted yf it be ſtubb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rne. Nowe if the magiſtrat ſo be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded to warre agaynſte them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do diſcei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer from him, verely than it is not vnlawfull to reſcue the churche by warre in caſe any barbarus prince come vpon it with open warre, to ſedewce it from trewe religion to erroure. Ioſue went a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bout to expugne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rubenites only for an aulter erected agaynſte the word of god.<note place="margin">Ioſue xxii a</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. Macha. v.</note>Iudas Machabeus doth fyghte for the people of god agaynſte the gentiles and kyng Antiochus hys ſouldiers whoſe purpoſe<note place="margin">i. Mac iii.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11367:14"/> was to vanquyſhe the Iewes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, whiche than was onelye true, and to place in the ſteade of it ſuperſtitious gentylyte.<note place="margin">Actium, xv</note> So Paule doth commende the captai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes which through fayth w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtode the incurſions of forain enemies. And Paule hym ſelf had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flyct in Cyprus agaynſt Elimas a falſe prophete whome alſo he ſtroke with blyndnes:<note place="margin">act. xiii.</note> And hys reaſon foloweth that he dydde it for relygyons ſake.<note place="margin">act, xiiii.</note> Wylte thou not ceaſe, ſayth he, to ſubuerte the ſtreyghte wayes of the Lorde. Agaynſte the ſame Paule there were fourtye men conſpyred,<note place="margin">act, xxiii, v. c.</note> whyche thoughte that yf he were take oute of the waye / a greate parte of CHRISTES re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygyon were abolyſhed, and their iudicyall relygyon ſette
<pb facs="tcp:11367:15"/> vp againe. But Paule here play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not the ſhepe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um. xxiii</note> nor turneth not the other cheke to them but was erneſte and ſollicitous to aſke his defence and that not of a chriſtian magiſtrate,<note place="margin">Yf Paule aſked helpe of an ethnik magiſtra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, more myght <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e do of a chryſtyan</note> but a romayne centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rion: neither ſhewed he him ſelfe any thynge greued therat, whan lxx. horſemen and .cccc. fotemen. were prepared for him in battayle ray to conduct him from Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem to Antipatrida.<note n="*" place="margin">act ix b and xxii b <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a i</note> Thus was Paule the elect veſſell preſerued by an Armed Gariſon of romain ſouldiours. Concerninge the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menians, ſufferynge greate vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of Maximinus the empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure. Euſebius ſo writeth in his eccleſiaſtical hiſtorie .li.ix.c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.viii. They Armenians ſayth he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ons a people kind and frendly to the pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of Rome,<note place="margin">eccl. ix <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> viii</note> what tyme they
<pb facs="tcp:11367:15"/> ſhuld be conſtrayned of Maximi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus the Emperour to change the ſtate of chriſtian relygion (to the which they were al gyuen to) into worſhipping of Idoles, and to ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rat deuyls for god, beyng hys tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>des before waxed hys greate enemies, and of their awne accord toke vpon theim wyth ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might of warre to withſtand his wicked conſtraynment, and ſo kepte hym hard. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hys ſayth Euſebius. Therfore the magiſtrates maye lawfully defende their ſubiectes and true religion agaynſt idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
            <p>Or els an other cauſe is which is much lyke.<note place="margin">The thyrde cauſe of warre</note> ſome foreine &amp; Barba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous aduerſary doth fly vpon thy ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ectes / doth ſpoyle them, and inuadith them / as the cruel wol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues do the ſhepe, whan not onlye
<pb facs="tcp:11367:16"/> thou haſte not prouoked them with anye iniuries, but moreouer haſt offered them righte reſonable conditions of peace, than oughte the magiſtrat to ſtyrte lyke a Lio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to preſerue hys people agaynſte the aſſaultes of ſuche malytiouſe murderers. Example we haue of Moſes feightyng againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Amorites Aradeus Seon,<note place="margin">Num, xxi, and xxxii. deut, ii c and, iii, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> and og. Example we haue of kynge Ioſaphat feyghtyng a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ammonites,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Para, xx.</note> and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of mount Seir; Example we haue alſo in Dauid reſiſtynge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Sitians comi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpon hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth warre.<note place="margin">
                  <p>ii reg x. c</p>
                  <p>The .iiii, cauſe of war</p>
               </note> Fourthly it is lawful for the magiſtrate to feyght in the defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his confederat frendes &amp; ayders, (for why may not a magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate be at confederacy and leyge wyth other nacions ſo it be not
<pb facs="tcp:11367:16"/> in matters againſte the worde of god) in caſe they be iuſtlye oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> violence. So did Ioſue delyuer the Gabonities from Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yge,<note place="margin">Ioſua, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. i. reg xi</note> and Saul the cyteſyns of Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes Galaad, warrynge agaynſte Naas a prince of great tyranny. For ſuch cauſes warres may law<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully be attempted of magiſtrates and prynces. And the ſouldiours do wel whiche herein obeye their powers, yea and dye gloriouſlye and in a good ſtate, in ſo dyenge for religion, for goddes lawes, for their countre, theire wyffes &amp; chyldren. Therfore all ſuch as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into warre, and trauell in the ſame, muſt not ſet their eye eyther vpon fylthy lucre nor voluptouſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">An inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion for ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers</note> as they lyghtly do whan Ieoperdy is paſt, but iuſtice, pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, publike tranquyllite, and
<pb facs="tcp:11367:17"/> the defence of truth and innocen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy muſt be al their marke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhute at: ſo that the wycked ſorte beyng conquered, the victory got. and their enemies other r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pulſed or deſtroyed, true religion maye floryſh in iudgement and equitie, the church may floryſh, diuine la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes rites inſtitutes, and eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtike ordinaunces maye flo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yſhe, ſtudies and good artes may proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pere, the poore may be ſeen to: the widowes and ſuccourleſſe chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren may be helped, that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may lyue in reſt, may ſerue and prayſe god, both aged perſons, chaiſte maydens and honeſt matrones. To this marke ought al our eyes both of mynd and body. to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected. Theſe thinges had our va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liaunt forefathers in their ſight whanſoeuer they made any warre
<pb facs="tcp:11367:17"/> agaynſt the wycked for their eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſtik and publik ryght, as Abra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ham, Moſes, Ioſue, Dauyd, and other noble captaynes, alſo oure progenitours before vs, to whom and to all ſuch other valiant ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diers perpetuall fame and laude ought to be gyuen in the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of ſaynctes,</p>
            <p>But to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other towardes &amp; ſloug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſh ſouldiers, wicked, couitouſe, blaſphemers, riotous, &amp; light ruffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and betrayers, which by their ſlougyſhnes, riote, lechery, and im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pietie diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>roy many noble realms, now a days, and many floriſhing cyties, to ſuche be continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke, and god hym ſelfe hath cur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed ſuch wycked catyffes for euer. Therfore no warre is lawfull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be againſt our aduerſaries
<pb facs="tcp:11367:18"/> and miſordered rebellers. Vniuſt warres be ſuch as be made agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt our owne fellowes or men faute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,<note place="margin">vniuſt war<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res</note> or in whom we ſe hope of ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Alſo vniuſt warres be thei which be not inferred after a dew maner, or for any vrgent cauſe. All maner of ways oughte to be aſſayed tyrſte, before we come to warre.<note place="margin">An inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ates,</note> You muſt not ſeke to take in other mennes bondes or limit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes nothing pertainynge to youre ryght. You muſt not oppreſſe the liberti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of other nations neither yet of your owne. Suche affectes whiche ſeduce the mynde are not here to be folowed, as gredines of dominion, auarice deſire of bribes enuye, or any ſuche other lyke to theſe. Warre is a remedy, but dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gerouſe, a helpe, but pernitiouſe, muche lyke to the cuttynge of of
<pb facs="tcp:11367:18"/> members. In caſe thy hande be on fyer, and ſo thy arme be in dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger to be brent and afterwarde the whole man lykewiſe, yet doeſte y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> not cutte away thy hand ſtreyght wayes onleſſe thou ſee, prouynge al maner of wayes, no other helpe to be. So nether is warre to be ſet vpon but where there is no other remedy, ſo yet that princes remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre, they do nothinge which after wylbe to late. For iuſt warres be not repugninge to goddes worde in ſomuch that it deſcribeth to vs the lawes of warrefarre, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtreth to vs many goodly exam<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples of wars of wiſe and worthye captaines. In deu. xx.<note place="margin">deu. xx, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, xxi</note> we haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of war profitable &amp; neceſſary. ſo cleare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei nede no expoſition Many other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rules alſoo we may gather out of ſcriptur as theſ Principally &amp; aboue al things let relygion
<pb facs="tcp:11367:19"/> be moſt obſerued in the campe.</p>
            <p>Iuſt lawes no leſſe oughte to be kept in the middeſte of warres as in the middeſt of cities, the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours let them kepe them in due or<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre with all honeſty,<note place="margin">Rue, iii b</note> iuſtice, &amp; holi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. For this prouerbe is of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll, not of god that ſome do ſaye. <hi>Sileant inter arma leges.</hi> Lawes kepe ſilence in warre. The cheife captayne generall let hym be cho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſen a godly man, iuſt, holly valy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt, ſapient, and luckey, as was Ioſue, Dauid. Iudas Machabe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>us, Conſtantinus. Theodoſius, Maſcelſer &amp; many other let there be appointed to hym an armye of tryed men.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wling ſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>diours</note> For in chuſyng of ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diours great circumſpeccion is to be hadde, that they be not a compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny of weyklinges, vnſkylful war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous, vnfaythful, blaſphemers
<pb facs="tcp:11367:19"/> wicked wretches, dronken glut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons, and beaſtely bellyes.</p>
            <p>Victory goyth not by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but by the grace of god<note place="margin">Vyctori go<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>eth by grace not by multi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tude gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e: iiii d Iudy. vii a i, reg. xvii</note> and by godly ſouldiers: it is an olde prouerb, wher is a multytud, ther is confuſion. Great and innu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>merable hoſtes do but combre and diſtroye themſelues. Experience &amp; exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the old tyme teach this ſufficiently. Agayn ſuch warriers as wyll take no payne be lu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kiſh lubbers, be greatly to be dyſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendid. Therfore lett euer a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiane warrioure be doynge ſome<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng, let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be corrageous, fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful paynful obediente to his cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne muſt neuer let ſlyppe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion well practiſed in the feytes of warre not tendre but harde, not cruell and fearſe. but graue &amp; gen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyl accordyng as tyme doth ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:11367:20"/> The thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be ſauyd let him not deſtroye. But aboue all other eſpecially let hym not forget con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually to praye vnto god, bothe in ieopardy and owt of ieoperdy let hym begyn all thynges in the lord,<note place="margin">a warryer muſt do all th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nges in the name of the lorde</note> and without the lord let him attempt nothinge: in miſfortune he muſt not be diſcouraged, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> proſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perouſe ſucceſſe, let hym not be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, but gyue thankes to god &amp; vſe hys victory w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mercy, let his vyctorye onelye ſtande in god &amp; not in hym ſelfe. let hym ſeke for nothyng more than for defenſe of hys countrye, of lawes, of religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of iuſtice, and of innocentes. Some here wyll meruell I dare ſaye that I requyre theſe thyngs of ſouldyours, whiche were wont in tymes paſte to be requyred of
<pb facs="tcp:11367:20"/> religious and profeſſed men.</p>
            <p>As thoughe ſouldiours were not alſo religious and profeſſed to chriſt, or as though only they mai be profane and wicked, as indede many of them be. But what frui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes I praye you come of this ſyde we be ouercome of Turckes. we be a mockingſtoke to all nations, whole kyngdomes peryſſhe, and be ſubdued to Mahometes lawe, and we be daylye intangled in greate perplexities, what maner of ſouldiers in tyme paſte were chuſon to warre out of the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of chriſtians, it appeareth by one memorable hyſtorye of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullianus wrytynge thus to Sca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pula.</p>
            <p>Marcus Aurelius alſoo warrynge in Germany,<note place="margin">The maner of ſouldy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s in olde tyme</note> thorough the prayers of chriſtian ſouldiers
<pb facs="tcp:11367:21"/> made to god, obtayned rayne in great drought.<note place="margin">The maner o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſoudiours in olde tyme.</note> And what drough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes can any man ſay but were ſtop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped throughe oure prayers &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyngs? than they alſo which cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to their great god in the name of iuppiter dyd gyue teſtimonye to our god. Thus much ſaith Ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tullia.<note place="margin">Euſebius lib. v ca, v</note> The ſame hyſtory doth Eu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſebius alſo more largelye expreſſe in his eccleſiaſtick boke. v. cap. v ſaynge, it chaunſed, ſayth he, Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cus Aurelius: the brother of An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toninus themperour hadde warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with the germanes, and Serma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens,<note place="margin">Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>table mi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>racle of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ours</note> the ſtoryes wytneſſe, that his hoſte was in great daunger for drought and drynes, and as he was conſultyng and ſeking what to be done he founde certayn chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian ſouldiours in the campe whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che whan they kneeled downe as
<pb facs="tcp:11367:21"/> our faſhion is and prayed to god ſodenly agaynſte all expectation rayne powred downe, their thyrſt was quentched their enemies dry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen away with lightninge &amp; fyer. This ſame ſtory is alſo written in the monimentes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gentyls but that it came by the prayers of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians they make no mencion ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of, as whych gyue lyttel credence to al other miracles of chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tertuliane ſo doth writte it plainli to come by them. So doth Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linaris alſo a greike whiche ſayth moreouer, that the ſame armey for the great myracle ſhewed in it, was called of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lightni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fulminia by themperour hym ſelfe. Tertul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lianus addyth moreouer that the piſtle of Marcus the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perour was a brode, wher in this myracle is ſignified more euidentlye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:22"/>
            <p>Thus much hath euſebius, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we may ſee howe chriſten ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diours in time paſt, not only were all bent to prayer, but alſo full of al iuſtice and hollynes of lyfe. It is euident that ſ. Iames ſaythe: The prayer of the iuſt doth much auayle.<note place="margin">Iacob. v, c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Helias was a man as we be, and he prayed, by and by the heauen gaue rayne, and the earth gaue his fruyte.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i reg. xviii.</note> Wherfore it is manyfeſt that the olde ſouldiours than were religiouſe and deuoute men, but our ſouldiours bycauſe they be farre from al religion yea enemyes to true relygion therfore in ſteade of vyctores they bring a way ouerthrowes both of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and cities.<note place="margin">Worke well you citiſens</note> And ſo the citeſens be wel &amp; worthely ſerued for that they put their confidence in ſuche wycked warriours which is euen as much
<pb facs="tcp:11367:22"/> as yf they ſhulde put their confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in very deuyls,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f, par, xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> whome theſe almoſt excede in al filthenes, cruel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and al wycked artes.<note place="margin">examples of godly wars warryoure, taken out of ſcrypture</note>
            </p>
            <p>Examples of holy &amp; iuſte warre, of holly &amp; iuſt captaynes we haue aboundant in the word of god &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moſte innumerable? Abraham our predeceſſor armed with a ſmal hoſt doth ſet vpon four y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt mighty kynges or robbers of al the world doth ouerthrow them &amp; dryue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away,<note place="margin">gene. xliii.</note> reſtoryth hys awne men w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their goods gyuinge thankes to god the author of ſuche an vncre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible victory. Moſes with Ioſue<note place="margin">Ioſua: x. and</note> doth throw down about thirtye &amp; nyne kynges, doth punyſhe wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes ſharply,<note place="margin">Num. xxi, &amp; xxxi, &amp;c,</note> do place their peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple in their lande promiſed of god.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:23"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iud. i, ii. tit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii. vi vii viii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole boke.</note>The iudges of iſraelites dydde kepe worthy warres againſte the ethnickes and infideles: and in them did aſſwage the tirannye of the wycked with which tirrannye they oppreſſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chyldren of god, &amp; reſtored y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people to their liberty &amp; religion.<note place="margin">i reg, vli viii and xii &amp;c</note> Here commeth alſo Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>muel a worthy prophet amongeſt the noble captaines of gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.<note place="margin">i reg xiiii xviii xviiii xx xxiii &amp;c</note> Ionathas the ſonne of Saul was a noble captain, a notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of godlynes. Who was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a more excellent captaine than Dauid he conquered the philiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,<note place="margin">i reg xvii &amp; xx<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ii reg v viii xxi &amp;c i par xv <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ii regr</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Ammonites and the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and a greate part of the eaſt with his warres both reuenging iniuries reſtorynge againe liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, and puttynge awaie innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable euyls from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of god<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And yet he that dyd al this is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:11367:23"/> a man after gods owne harte ye and the<note n="*" place="margin">i reg vii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> romia ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> father of our lord.<note place="margin">i regr evi e pſalltre ix e ac um xiii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus chriſt after the fleſh.</p>
            <p>In the poſteritie of Dauid ye ſhal fynde notable warriours, &amp; ſyngu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar captaynes, Abias Aſas, Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat Amaſias. Oſias. Eſechias with many other.</p>
            <p>Iudas machabeus amongeſt all other is not the vnwortheyſt why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſtode ſo valiantly for the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes of god for gods relygion,<note place="margin">i macha iiiiiiiv vt viiiviiii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> &amp; for the peoples right and at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth was ſlayne in Aſia for the rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the people of god. Yt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyth not to ade herto the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples for Conſtantinus, Gratianus, Theodoſius, and other puiſſant princes. Of theſe and ſuche other S. Auguſtine in his bocke de,<note place="margin">auguſt the ciuitate dei lib v</note> Ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uitate dei. Lib. v. Hath wrytten a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boundantlye, and Oroſius lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:11367:24"/> in his hiſtory.<note place="margin">Oroſius, libra, vii, cap xxviii</note> Li. vii. From y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> xxviii. Cap. Vnto the ende. This I thynk ſufficient for good magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates. Thus far I haue entrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of warre howe magiſtrates ought to vſe them ſelues, and con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cernynge the vſe of the ſword,</p>
            <p>Wherof alſo I haue ſpoken ſome what, in my ſermon vpon the fifte commaundement.</p>
            <p>Theſe thynges thus beyng con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded now we wyll diſcuſſe, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be lawful for chriſtianes to beare offyce or not and eſpecially for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> occaſion of ceartain furious Anabaptyſtes, &amp; new diuiſors of new found commenweales, which all eage againſte vs that it is not lawful for chriſtianes to be magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates bycauſe chriſtianes do not contende in the market, neither do kyl anye man, neyther ſeke again
<pb facs="tcp:11367:24"/> there goodes taken awaye, nether reuenge their iniuties. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though theſe places of theirs be anſwered vnto ſufficiently,<note place="margin">It is lafull for chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to be magi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtrates</note> yet I brynge here ſuccinctlye certayne argumentes, wherby a polityke &amp; chriſtiane man againſt the fury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous dreames of the Anabaptiſtes may vnderſtand, yf he be called to offyce, that he may and ought to ſerue god well in kepinge &amp; well vſinge his offyce.</p>
            <p>For where as they fayne no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of defence to be lawfull by the goſpel they be farre deceyued for the veryte ſayth otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>For what thynges ſo euer be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of God to the healthe and ſaffety of man, they be ſo ſeyming to a chrſtiane man vſyng theme wel &amp; appleyng him ſelfe thera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter
<pb facs="tcp:11367:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> that if he refuſe them, he is no tru chriſtian. For the greateſt charge of a chriſtiane. is to ſet forwarde with al induſtry the ſauegarde &amp; welth of men,<note place="margin">Capi di a prou xxiiii c and xx a tuum iii a i p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>try i. v</note> Now the magiſtrat is ordeined of no man but of god him ſelfe to the ſauegarde &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection of men. As expreſſely it is witneſſed by the prophetes and a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſtles and paule eſpeciallye Ad rom. xiii who ſo doth not ſee than but a chriſtiane maye laudably<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beare the office of a magiſtrate. Forthermore no man wyl deny I thinke that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to euery chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten man to declare his faythe not only with woordes, but wyth the workes of iuſtice and mercy, to ſee for the publicke peace &amp; tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quilite to folow iuſtice &amp; equite, to defend wydowes, the fatherles, &amp; expreſſed. Neyther oughte he to
<pb facs="tcp:11367:25"/> neglect occaſion, place, or any ſuch meane, wherby he maye exercyſe ſuch benefites vpon his brethren Therfore it is not vnknowe that a chriſtiane may be a magiſtrate. For the office of a magiſtrate is to e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecute iudgement, and iuſtice, and to mayntaine publyke peace.</p>
            <p>Fow it is out of doubt and pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued before,<note place="margin">Worke wel</note> that Moſes, Samuel Ioſue, and Dauid, &amp; other more, are not to be excluded from the name of chriſtians, than ſeynge they were magiſtrates, why may not chriſten men as well nowe a days beare office<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>In the newe teſtament m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ny no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men be commendid which wer in rule and authorite, neyther yet dyd they renounce their office by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of religion.<note place="margin">Luce xxxii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſeph of Aramatheus thus we reede in
<pb facs="tcp:11367:26"/> Luc. Beholde there was a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led Ioſeph a Centurion (ſ. marke ſayth a ſenatour) a good man and iuſt,<note place="margin">mar xv</note> &amp; he conſented not to theyr counſel and doinges borne, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramathea a citye of the iewes, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch alſo dyd loke for the kyngdom of god. Note here what a greate commendation is giuen hym.</p>
            <p>Ioſeph is a Centurion, or a ſena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and that an honeſt ſenator<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he dyd ſy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te in the counſel houſe and amongeſt theſe iudges which con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demned chriſt, but bycauſe he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented not with them he is excuſed gyltles from the bloude, the ſame alſo is notefied to be a good man and iuſte, in the numbre of them, whiche loked for the kyngedome of god that is, in the numbre of chriſtianes, and for all this was he yet a Centurion or a ſenatoure
<pb facs="tcp:11367:26"/> and dwelled in the citie of Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. A chriſtian therfore lawful lye may beare office. Hereto maye be broughte examples of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes chamberlayne of Aethiopia. Actum. viii.<note place="margin">actum, viii.</note> of cornelius the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turione. Actum. x.<note place="margin">ctum x</note> of Euraſtus the warden or ſtuarde of the cytie of Corinthe. Rom. xvi.ii,<note place="margin">rom. xvi i. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tum ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Timo. iiii But I wolde the Anabaptiſtes wolde proue that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſcriptures which they obiect, that theſe being conuerted after didde lay downe their robbe and ſworde. For we haue proued it before by ſ. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines wordes vpon the aunſwer of Ihon Baptiſt to the ſouldiers which was alſo a chriſten preeher that after they were baptiſed,<note place="margin">luc iii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Ihon, ii<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> yet notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtandinge were not depoſed from their office neither had anye ſuche commaundemente of Ihon to forſake their warre farre.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:27"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The lord re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſed to be made a king</note>And other obiection they haue, bycauſe the lord did withdraw hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe, what tyme the people inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to make hym kynge. Whiche thing he wold not haue done,<note place="margin">Ihon. vi. v</note> but to gyue example to all chriſtians of humilitie, and to commaunde in a maner neuer to ſuffre any pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke adminiſtration to be put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, to this they adde the lai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynges or the goſpell. My kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is not of this worlde.<note place="margin">Ihon. xviii c</note> Item The kynges of the earth rayne o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them but you not lo.<note place="margin">mat. x. d, mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>c luc. x<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i v. art l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, i, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. v. a</note>
            </p>
            <p>Truth it is the lord a voyded the people. But howe folowynge the way that was not reighte, neither intending to do the wyll of god, but blynded with carnal affectes, and ſekyng ſuch thinges as were pertaynyng to belycheare. Forby cauſe he fedde them wonderfully / 
<pb facs="tcp:11367:27"/> therfore they thought hym a mete kynge for their purpoſe, whyche could fede his ſubiectes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> much fare and no coſt.<note place="margin">math, xx, d.</note> Beſides this our lorde came not to beare rule in earth, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faſhyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this world as the Iewes imagined, thinking that Meſſias ſhoulde come lyke Salomon, here to reigne, and as Pilate feared.</p>
            <p>Therfore ſayde the lorde wel.<note place="margin">Ihon. xviii e</note> My kyngdome is not of this worlde.<note n="*" place="margin">actum i, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mat xxvi f ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, xxv in c tam viii, e ephe. i, iiii</note> For he aſcended vp to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teth on the right hande of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, hauyng al kynges ſubiected to hym, and al the worlde, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che now he rayneth by hys worde and ſpirite, whiche alſo he ſhall come to iudge at the laſte daye.<note place="margin">mat xxv: c rom, xiii, d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, vltimo, iiiii, a i pet, iiii a ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. x..</note>
            </p>
            <p>And although chriſt denyeth hys kyngdome to be of this world, yet he neuer denyed but that kynges
<pb facs="tcp:11367:28"/> and princes of the worlde ſhoulde come into his churche, in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they ſhuld ſerue the lorde, not only as men but as kynges and prynces. For kyngs can not ſerue the lorde as kinges otherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by exercyſyng that wherfore they be made kynges. And vnleſſe chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtian kynges myghte remayne in their office. and gouerne kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes after their rule and lawes of chriſte how coulde chriſt be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the kynge of kings, &amp; lorde of lordes. Therfore where the lorde ſaid, the kynges of the earthe do raygne ouer them but you not ſo, he ſpake this only to hys apoſtles ſtryuyng for ſuperiorite, as thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghe he would ſay. Prynces rayg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge in the worlde be not putte down from their thrones &amp; ſeates by my doctrine.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:28"/>
            <p>For mi doctryne doth not abolyſh polycie / office, nor magiſtrate in the world or in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate he ſhall raigne, but you not ſo, you ſhal not raygne, ye ſhal not be princes, but teachers of the worlde, and ſeruauntes of the chu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rche. Thus in fewe wordes haue we anſwered to the obiections of the Anabaptyſtes, which we haue confuted alſo in other places. He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto I thynk it ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that a chriſten man not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly maye, but oughte alſo to beare rule and office, yf it be ryghtfully offered vnto hym.</p>
            <p>But before we knyt vp this diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">The daie of ſubiectes.</note> we wil touch now breifly what is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of ſubiectes, what euery one oweth to his magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te. Fyrſt it is the parte of ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, to haue a reuerende and
<pb facs="tcp:11367:29"/> honorable eſtimation of their prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and powers. And ſo to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence them as goddes meſſyngers and miniſtres. Alſo outwardly to exhibite ſuche homage vnto them as euery mans countreye requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth. It is a foule thinge yf ſubie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes vnreuerently ſhulde behaue theim ſelues to their magiſtrates. But a falſe and a lyghte opinion ones conceiued of any thing doth ſoone brynge a contempte of the ſame: Therefore here be to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered certayne open teſtimonies of the ſcripture, wherby to engen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre into euery mans mynd a dewe exiſtimation and reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce toward hys magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>Here nowe all princes and ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious muſt take hede leſt through their vnſemeable and diſſolute lyfe they bringe them ſelues into
<pb facs="tcp:11367:29"/> contempt / &amp; ſo by theire owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault leſe al their authoritie amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the people. Trulye god hym ſelfe diſdaineth not to cal princes and rulers by his awn propre na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me euen gods the places be Exo, xxi. and Pſal. lxxxii.<note place="margin">Exod, xxi. Pſal. lxxxii.</note> The apoſtles called them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meſſengers and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places be. Ro. xiii i. Pet, ii.<note place="margin">Rom xiii a i pet ii b</note> Who wyl not magnifye with al reuerence gods, and gods myniſters, thorough, whome he worketh ſaluation to the people. He that reiecteth the meſſinger, re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctyth him which ſent hym. Who ſo honoreth the meſſenger, ſemeth to beſtowe his honor moſt vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſender. Alſo ſaith Salomon. pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. xvi.<note place="margin">prou. xvi</note> Diuination is in the lyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes of the kinge therfore his hart doth not tranſgreſſe. And. Eccleſi. viii.<note place="margin">eccleſi viii</note> it is my parte to obſerue the
<pb facs="tcp:11367:30"/> commaundement of the kynge, &amp; to haue regard to the othe of god. Item prou. xxiiii.<note place="margin">Prou xxiiii</note> Mi chyld feare god, and feare thy kynge and ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pe no reſorte with the ſclaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers. For their perdition ſhall ryſe quickly.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. xiii.</note> Saint Paul likwiſe Whoſoeuer ſayth he reſiſteth the hyer powers reſiſteth gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and they which ſhall reſiſt that, ſhall receiue to theym ſelues iudgement. Concernyng this mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter I haue entreated alſo vppon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> v. commaundement, Than let the ſubiectes pray for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princes &amp; ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giſtrates y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god may graunt them ſapience,<note place="margin">ſubiectes to praye for theire prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces</note> prudence fortitude, tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce iuſtice, dew ſeuerite meik<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes and other vertues, to leade the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in hys wayes and preſerue them from all euyll that we maye lyue peaceably &amp; honeſtly in this world
<pb facs="tcp:11367:30"/> This doth ſ. paule requyre of ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, i. Timo. ii.<note place="margin">i timo. ii Iere, xxix,</note> And Ierem. xxix Many be ſlouthfull and negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent in this part and that maketh them ſome tyme to be pynched &amp; feyle that they wold not. And wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thely. For yf they wolde do theyr deutye in prayng for their magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates earneſtly / they ſhuld haue better, In the olde church what a feruent ſtudy they had to pray for their magiſtrat the wordes of Ter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tullianus in his Apo. ca. xxx doth wel declare,<note place="margin">tertul. apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geti. ca, xxx,</note> ſaynge. Let vs pray always for al rulers, &amp; kynges &amp; Emperours, that they maye haue longe lyfe, a quiet raigne, a ſayfe houſe, valiant ſouldiours, fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full counſailers, honeſt ſubiectes, a peaceable world, &amp; what ſo euer man or Emperour or kyng would haue obtayned.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:31"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Obedience of ſubiectes</note>Subiectes alſo ought to obei the lawes of magiſtrates yf they be good &amp; equale and ſo to obeye them, that it be with al holy reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and harty religion, as obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge not the lawes of men but of gods miniſters.<note place="margin">i pet ii b</note> For Peter byd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs be obedient for the lorde.<note place="margin">rom xiii b Titum iii</note> And Paule ſayth ſubiectes muſte be obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t not only for diſpleaſur but alſo for conſcience ſake. That is we muſt obeye oure magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. not only for feare leaſt we be punyſhed for contempte and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, but leſte we ſynne agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nſte god and our owne conſcience condempne vs. We declared be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the fifte commaundement by diuerſe teſtimonies &amp; examples of ſcripture, that we be not bownd to obeye the commaundemente of magiſtrates,<note place="margin">We be not bounde to o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bey magiſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rates in thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry to god</note> in thinges vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful
<pb facs="tcp:11367:31"/> and againſt the worde of god The Apoſtles and chriſtianes of the primatiue church wold rather be impriſoned, baniſhed,<note place="margin">Rom viii <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ii cor iiii and v pſa xliiii e</note> ſpoyled deuoured of beaſtes, ſlayne wyth ſword, burned with fier and han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, than to obey wycked and vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lawful commaundementes. The bleſſed martyr and byſhop Poly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carpus<note place="margin">Polycarpus</note> anſweringe to the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul of Rome ſaid. Our doctrin is, ſayth he, to princes &amp; powers ſuch as be of god to gyue honor, ſuch honor as is not contrarye to the rule of our religion.</p>
            <p>And Ihon Chriſoſtome<note place="margin">Chryſoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to Gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam ſayd. Yt is not lawful for an Emperour whiche is the mayne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiner of godlynes, to attempt ani thynge agaynſte the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes of god.</p>
            <p>Fynally Subiectes let them giue<note place="margin">Subei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to pay trybute</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:11367:32"/> to the magiſtrat tribute, yea their bodies and lyfe alſo whan nede is for the defence of their mage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, &amp; countre, as I declared in the .v. commaundement, the lorde expreſſely commaundeth in the goſpel. Giue to god thoſe thinges which are gods,<note place="margin">mark xxii, e and xvii d, rom xiii b</note> &amp; to themperoure the thinges which are the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours. Whoſo euer be ſlacke ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, or any thynge drawynge backe in this part they be greatly to be reproued, Tributes be dewe to the magiſtrate as the rewarde of his labor, and as the ſynewe of publick vtilite and quietnes. For what man euer goyth to warre v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his awne charge and ſtipend. Euery man lyueth vpon his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor which he ſuſteneth. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrat doth labor the prynce doth labour in gouerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth
<pb facs="tcp:11367:32"/> and kepyng peace. He omytteth his owne priuate buſines at home wherby els he myght prouyde for him ſelfe. Therfore it wer againſt al reaſon yf he ſhulde not be main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayned with publike charges. Al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo it is requiſet that kyngdomes &amp; publik weales be well appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with ſufficient ryches,<note place="margin">Rycheſſe be neceſſary <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o the publyke word.</note> to ayde them with al in warres, in dearth, in fyers and other calamites, in reparations, or in repellyng of greater daungers, here I ſpeake nothing now of publike buyldin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges as of kepynge vp the walles fortreſſes, trenches, diches haue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s brygges, hye ways, fountaynes, condithes, the court haull, the mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ket place, with many other.</p>
            <p>There be alſo publike officers of iuſtice, as ſergeantes, herodes of armes, watchemen and
<pb facs="tcp:11367:33"/> diuerſe ſuch moo wher as yf mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney be not preſent, how can any kyngdome and commen wealthe ſtand longe.<note place="margin">Richer work men</note> Therfore they why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che deny trybute, deny the dew ſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pend of mens labour, yea &amp; ſeke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſubuerſion of the comen wealthe. They which be ſlack and vnluſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful in publik labours &amp; workes, do ſynne not agaynſte one ruler, but agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> come<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nalte. And commenly it is ſo ſeene ſuch lyſtles &amp; lither labourers lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel to be bleſſed of god and ſeldom to thryue.</p>
            <p>Yet mageſtrates &amp; princes here muſt be aduertiſed, to loue their ſubiectes committed to their faith and tuition, to ſpare them as gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyllye as they can, to beare with them, and not to pyntche them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to importunat exactiones.<note place="margin">exactions</note> Thys
<pb facs="tcp:11367:33"/> may be done, yf they wylbe tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and abſtayne from all ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fluouſe exceſſe and pryde. Lette a good prynce thus conſidre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe,<note place="margin">a goodly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces</note> howe vnequal it is for his courte to ouerflowe all, withal ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſe and ſuperfluyte, and all hys other cyties and ſubiectes to be pi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched by the belly at home. Let ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of realmes remembre, tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, taxes &amp; cuſtomes to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyke and not priuate goodes.</p>
            <p>God hateth pollers and extorcio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners. God abhorreth vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble exactions, taxes or tolles. God doth execrate tyrannies ſtyll pyle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>linge the people. He doth bleſſe gentyl and moderate prynces.</p>
            <p>The iuſt concorde of ſubie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes auayleth more in pea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and out of peace,<note place="margin">A golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſentence</note> than
<pb facs="tcp:11367:34"/> monye vniuſt. And ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger is the realm with leſſe aboundaunce,<note place="margin">Good ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>biectes marke this leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> and more concorde betwyxt the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours and inferiours, than with infinite treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, where magiſtrates &amp; ſubiectes do not agree.</p>
            <p>This is no lye / Commen experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence teſtifieth the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thus much good audience, haue I entreated concernyng magiſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes vpon the occaſion of the ſyxte commaundement thou ſhalt not kyl declaring as brefly as I culd vnder your charitable audience, why magiſtrates be ordeyned of god, what is their duety to their ſubiectes. What is the deutye of
<pb facs="tcp:11367:34" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſubiectes to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Now let vs proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trat our ſupplication to god that of his clemency he wyl ſo graunte both to the magiſtrates &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iectes, that they maye both walke worthy to their vocation.</p>
            <closer>God graunt. Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="references">
            <p>☞Of ſedicion Inſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion, and rebellion, and their punyſhemente reade theſe places.</p>
            <p>Num, xvi fig. xx. a. Iudicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. ix. d. e. f. xii. a. b. ii. Reg. xx. iii. reg. i. a. i. Heſter. ii. d. Act. v. e. xix. c. xviii. b. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="quotations">
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶Seke peace, and enſue it.</p>
            <bibl>¶Pſalm. xxxiii. i, pet. iii.</bibl>
            <p>The feare of the Lord is the be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gynning of wiſdome,</p>
            <bibl>¶Pſal cxi. b. prou, ix, b. Iob, xxviii. c. Eccle. i, c,</bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶Impri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted for Gwalter Lynne dwellynge vpon Somers Kaye by Byllynges gate. In the yeare of our lord god. M.D.Xlix, The xxiii, day of Auguſt,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>❀Cum gratia &amp; priuilegio ad imprimendum ſolum</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:11367:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
